Are worms the heroes we didn't know we needed?
蚯蚓是我们不知道却需要的英雄吗？
Silent, slimy and wriggling, you might think that worms are good for nothing except bait on the end of a fishing rod.
沉默、黏滑、蠕动，你可能认为蚯蚓除了作鱼竿末端的鱼饵外毫无用处。
However, there is more to the humble worm than meets the eye.
然而，不起眼的蚯蚓却远非表面看起来那么简单。
The British naturalist Charles Darwin said that no other animal has "played such an important part in the history of the world as these lowly organised creatures".
英国博物学家查尔斯·达尔文曾说，没有其他动物"像这些低等生物一样，在世界历史上扮演过如此重要的角色"。
They have lived on Earth for 600 million years and have even survived five mass extinctions.
它们在地球上已经生活了6亿年，甚至挺过了五次大灭绝。
So, what do worms do that is so great?
那么，蚯蚓到底做了什么了不起的事呢？
Earthworms literally move the earth, and this is why farmers love them.
蚯蚓实际上在移动土壤，这就是农民喜爱它们的原因。
As they travel, they aerate the soil by loosening, mixing and oxygenating it, which increases the ground's capacity to hold and drain water.
它们在移动时，松动、混合、给土壤通气，这增加了土壤的持水和排水能力。
They are effectively a small but very efficient plough.
它们实际上是一个虽小但效率很高的犁。
But it's not just earthworms that deserve praise.
但值得称赞的不仅仅是蚯蚓。
In 2022, a group of scientists at the Margarita Salas Center for Biological Research isolated enzymes found in wax worm saliva which are plastic-eating.
2022年，玛加丽塔·萨拉斯生物研究中心的一组科学家分离出了蜡虫唾液中发现的吃塑料的酶。
These can break down polyethylene, a very common plastic that normally degrades over many years.
这些酶可以分解聚乙烯，这是一种非常常见的塑料，通常需要许多年才能降解。
It's hoped that by producing these enzymes on an industry-level scale, we will have a more environmentally friendly way to reduce plastic pollution.
人们希望通过将这些酶进行工业规模生产，我们将能以一种更环保的方式来减少塑料污染。
And worms are even inspiring the building industry.
蠕虫甚至还赋予建筑行业以灵感。
Bloodworms are small sea creatures which burrow into the mud of the ocean floor.
血虫是一种小型海洋生物，它们会挖洞进入海底的泥土中。
Scientists at the University of California, Santa Barbara have been studying their jaws, which are made up of 10% copper proteins and are so strong that they last the worm's entire five-year lifespan.
加州大学圣塔芭芭拉分校的科学家们一直在研究它们的颚，这些颚由10%的铜蛋白质组成，非常坚固，能伴随血虫度过整整五年的寿命。
Because of this research, engineers may start using the jaws as inspiration for the design and manufacture of materials like concrete.
因为这项研究，工程师们可能会开始以这些颚为灵感，用于设计和制造像混凝土这样的材料。
So, next time you see a worm, show it a little respect.
所以，下次你看到蠕虫时，对它表示一点敬意吧。
They really are changing the world!
它们真的在改变世界！